<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://ashterism.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://ashterism.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-04-16T08:10:10+00:00</updated><id>https://ashterism.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Ashterism</title><subtitle>A collection of thoughts and experiences on Astronomy, Hiking, Sustainability, and the like</subtitle><author><name>Musings by Ash</name></author><entry><title type="html">First astro timelapse</title><link href="https://ashterism.com/2025/03/20/first-timelapse.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="First astro timelapse" /><published>2025-03-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-03-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ashterism.com/2025/03/20/first-timelapse</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ashterism.com/2025/03/20/first-timelapse.html"><![CDATA[<p>test text</p>

<p>testing video wrapper - trying adding more text do see if that makes any difference to the layout if it’s wrapping. Nearly there.  And long enough.  Long enough indeed.</p>

<div class="video-wrapper">
  <iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/PmEsczIhK4I" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>
</div>

<p>testing 123</p>]]></content><author><name>Musings by Ash</name></author><category term="astro" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[test text]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A test blog post for hiking category</title><link href="https://ashterism.com/2025/03/05/test3.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A test blog post for hiking category" /><published>2025-03-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-03-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ashterism.com/2025/03/05/test3</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ashterism.com/2025/03/05/test3.html"><![CDATA[<p>Ipsum lorem etc etc
Etc yarda yarda</p>

<p>ab
bc
sd</p>

<h1 id="heading-of-some-sort">Heading of some sort</h1>

<div class="tip">
  <strong>Tip:</strong> This is a helpful tip!
</div>

<p>Normal text</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>[!Warning] Add a space
Whatever</p>

</blockquote>
<div class="markdown-alert markdown-alert-important"><p class="markdown-alert-title"><svg class="octicon octicon-report" viewBox="0 0 16 16" version="1.1" width="16" height="16" aria-hidden="true"><path d="M0 1.75C0 .784.784 0 1.75 0h12.5C15.216 0 16 .784 16 1.75v9.5A1.75 1.75 0 0 1 14.25 13H8.06l-2.573 2.573A1.458 1.458 0 0 1 3 14.543V13H1.75A1.75 1.75 0 0 1 0 11.25Zm1.75-.25a.25.25 0 0 0-.25.25v9.5c0 .138.112.25.25.25h2a.75.75 0 0 1 .75.75v2.19l2.72-2.72a.749.749 0 0 1 .53-.22h6.5a.25.25 0 0 0 .25-.25v-9.5a.25.25 0 0 0-.25-.25Zm7 2.25v2.5a.75.75 0 0 1-1.5 0v-2.5a.75.75 0 0 1 1.5 0ZM9 9a1 1 0 1 1-2 0 1 1 0 0 1 2 0Z"></path></svg> Important</p><p>Key information users need to know to achieve their goal.</p>
</div>

<div class="markdown-alert markdown-alert-note"><p class="markdown-alert-title"><svg class="octicon octicon-info" viewBox="0 0 16 16" version="1.1" width="16" height="16" aria-hidden="true"><path d="M0 8a8 8 0 1 1 16 0A8 8 0 0 1 0 8Zm8-6.5a6.5 6.5 0 1 0 0 13 6.5 6.5 0 0 0 0-13ZM6.5 7.75A.75.75 0 0 1 7.25 7h1a.75.75 0 0 1 .75.75v2.75h.25a.75.75 0 0 1 0 1.5h-2a.75.75 0 0 1 0-1.5h.25v-2h-.25a.75.75 0 0 1-.75-.75ZM8 6a1 1 0 1 1 0-2 1 1 0 0 1 0 2Z"></path></svg> Note</p><p>Highlights information that users should take into account, even when skimming.
And supports multi-line text.</p>
</div>

<div class="markdown-alert markdown-alert-tip"><p class="markdown-alert-title"><svg class="octicon octicon-light-bulb" viewBox="0 0 16 16" version="1.1" width="16" height="16" aria-hidden="true"><path d="M8 1.5c-2.363 0-4 1.69-4 3.75 0 .984.424 1.625.984 2.304l.214.253c.223.264.47.556.673.848.284.411.537.896.621 1.49a.75.75 0 0 1-1.484.211c-.04-.282-.163-.547-.37-.847a8.456 8.456 0 0 0-.542-.68c-.084-.1-.173-.205-.268-.32C3.201 7.75 2.5 6.766 2.5 5.25 2.5 2.31 4.863 0 8 0s5.5 2.31 5.5 5.25c0 1.516-.701 2.5-1.328 3.259-.095.115-.184.22-.268.319-.207.245-.383.453-.541.681-.208.3-.33.565-.37.847a.751.751 0 0 1-1.485-.212c.084-.593.337-1.078.621-1.489.203-.292.45-.584.673-.848.075-.088.147-.173.213-.253.561-.679.985-1.32.985-2.304 0-2.06-1.637-3.75-4-3.75ZM5.75 12h4.5a.75.75 0 0 1 0 1.5h-4.5a.75.75 0 0 1 0-1.5ZM6 15.25a.75.75 0 0 1 .75-.75h2.5a.75.75 0 0 1 0 1.5h-2.5a.75.75 0 0 1-.75-.75Z"></path></svg> Tip</p><p>Optional information to help a user be more successful.</p>
</div>

<div class="markdown-alert markdown-alert-important"><p class="markdown-alert-title"><svg class="octicon octicon-report" viewBox="0 0 16 16" version="1.1" width="16" height="16" aria-hidden="true"><path d="M0 1.75C0 .784.784 0 1.75 0h12.5C15.216 0 16 .784 16 1.75v9.5A1.75 1.75 0 0 1 14.25 13H8.06l-2.573 2.573A1.458 1.458 0 0 1 3 14.543V13H1.75A1.75 1.75 0 0 1 0 11.25Zm1.75-.25a.25.25 0 0 0-.25.25v9.5c0 .138.112.25.25.25h2a.75.75 0 0 1 .75.75v2.19l2.72-2.72a.749.749 0 0 1 .53-.22h6.5a.25.25 0 0 0 .25-.25v-9.5a.25.25 0 0 0-.25-.25Zm7 2.25v2.5a.75.75 0 0 1-1.5 0v-2.5a.75.75 0 0 1 1.5 0ZM9 9a1 1 0 1 1-2 0 1 1 0 0 1 2 0Z"></path></svg> Important</p><p>Crucial information necessary for users to succeed.</p>
</div>

<div class="markdown-alert markdown-alert-warning"><p class="markdown-alert-title"><svg class="octicon octicon-alert" viewBox="0 0 16 16" version="1.1" width="16" height="16" aria-hidden="true"><path d="M6.457 1.047c.659-1.234 2.427-1.234 3.086 0l6.082 11.378A1.75 1.75 0 0 1 14.082 15H1.918a1.75 1.75 0 0 1-1.543-2.575Zm1.763.707a.25.25 0 0 0-.44 0L1.698 13.132a.25.25 0 0 0 .22.368h12.164a.25.25 0 0 0 .22-.368Zm.53 3.996v2.5a.75.75 0 0 1-1.5 0v-2.5a.75.75 0 0 1 1.5 0ZM9 11a1 1 0 1 1-2 0 1 1 0 0 1 2 0Z"></path></svg> Warning</p><p>Critical content demanding immediate
user attention due to potential risks.</p>
</div>

<div class="markdown-alert markdown-alert-caution"><p class="markdown-alert-title"><svg class="octicon octicon-stop" viewBox="0 0 16 16" version="1.1" width="16" height="16" aria-hidden="true"><path d="M4.47.22A.749.749 0 0 1 5 0h6c.199 0 .389.079.53.22l4.25 4.25c.141.14.22.331.22.53v6a.749.749 0 0 1-.22.53l-4.25 4.25A.749.749 0 0 1 11 16H5a.749.749 0 0 1-.53-.22L.22 11.53A.749.749 0 0 1 0 11V5c0-.199.079-.389.22-.53Zm.84 1.28L1.5 5.31v5.38l3.81 3.81h5.38l3.81-3.81V5.31L10.69 1.5ZM8 4a.75.75 0 0 1 .75.75v3.5a.75.75 0 0 1-1.5 0v-3.5A.75.75 0 0 1 8 4Zm0 8a1 1 0 1 1 0-2 1 1 0 0 1 0 2Z"></path></svg> Caution</p><p>Negative potential consequences of an action.
Opportunity to provide more context.</p>
</div>]]></content><author><name>Musings by Ash</name></author><category term="hiking" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Ipsum lorem etc etc Etc yarda yarda]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Applying the 500 rule</title><link href="https://ashterism.com/2025/03/04/the-500-rule.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Applying the 500 rule" /><published>2025-03-04T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-03-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ashterism.com/2025/03/04/the-500-rule</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ashterism.com/2025/03/04/the-500-rule.html"><![CDATA[<p>Feeling encouraged from Saturday, I did some research on Sunday into how to improve the images by reducing (or avoiding) the trailing, and how to do stacking and processing.  I found that I should apply the ‘“500 rule”’ (which meant use 0.3sec exposure time), take a hundred or so images, and then stack them in astrophotography software.  Lastly I would need to do some basic processing to the images to “adjust the curves” and bring out the colours more and reduce the noise. Lots to learn then!</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The 500 rule is: max shutter speed = effective focal length / 500.</p>

  <p>I have a Canon R7 with a 1.6x crop factor, so my effective focal length (using a Skywatcher 200P/1000) is: 1.6*1000 = 1600.</p>

  <p>500 / 1600 = 0.3125 seconds.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Equipped with this knowledge, I lined up the scope on the nebula, and swapped in the camera.  It was a little misty, so the stars were not quite as clear as last week, especially through the optics, but I was able to focus using a high exposure and ISO setting.  I then reduced the settings back down to 0.3 and ISO 6400 and took 160+ shots.  I did this using HDR+ mode (for faster shooting) and holding down the shoot button on the Canon Connect app so I could avoid touching the camera and introducing wobble.</p>

<p>My phone screen kept locking and in so doing, causing Canon Connect to disconnect, and by the time I got it all back connected everything needed realigning.  Increasing the delay on the lock screen to 5 mins was probably my biggest learning tonight!</p>

<p>The single images at ⅓ sec exposure were underwhelming, but with some basic processing came out looking pretty great (for a beginner!). When I was first out, I also took another batch of 150+ shots using ¼ sec exposures incase there was wobble in the first set, but didn’t end up processing them.</p>

<p>There are a lot of YouTube videos on how to stack and/or process your images, and I found most to either skip some steps or following them returned errors for me.  My goal was to figure out how to “simply” stack the images into one, and then how to balance the contrast/ brightness / colours to bring out the nebula.  In the end I found this video which made using Siril simple and effective: <a href="https://youtu.be/aruMYnfhrjw?si=cEkNyEi9WV5TV7C6" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Basic astro image stacking and processing with Siril</a></p>

<p>I initially used Siril to do the stacking, and then tried processing the stacked image separately in Siril and Photoshop.  I got more depth of colour in Photoshop, but I personally preferred the cleaner, more ethereal feel of the Siril edit.  I definitely have a huge way to go,  I feel I’m starting to understand the process now, and it’s really encouraging to have achieved these pictures, especially without use of a tracker.</p>

<figure>
  <img src="/assets/images/25_03/25_03_04_01.png" alt="Orion nebula as a few dots in the sky" />
  <figcaption>1* ⅓ sec exposure, at 6400 ISO.</figcaption>
</figure>

<figure>
  <img src="/assets/images/25_03/25_03_04_02.png" alt="VOrion nebula with dust cloud visible in an ethereal shades of blue" />
  <figcaption>155* ⅓ sec exposure / 6400iso, stacked in Siril, and processed in Siril.  
</figcaption>
</figure>

<figure>
  <img src="/assets/images/25_03/25_03_04_04.png" alt="Similar image to above, but with reds and greens instead of blues" />
  <figcaption>As above, but post processed in Photoshop
</figcaption>
</figure>

<p>-END-</p>]]></content><author><name>Musings by Ash</name></author><category term="astro" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Feeling encouraged from Saturday, I did some research on Sunday into how to improve the images by reducing (or avoiding) the trailing, and how to do stacking and processing. I found that I should apply the ‘“500 rule”’ (which meant use 0.3sec exposure time), take a hundred or so images, and then stack them in astrophotography software. Lastly I would need to do some basic processing to the images to “adjust the curves” and bring out the colours more and reduce the noise. Lots to learn then!]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">First attempt at M42 Orion Nebula</title><link href="https://ashterism.com/2025/03/02/trying-orion.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="First attempt at M42 Orion Nebula" /><published>2025-03-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-03-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ashterism.com/2025/03/02/trying-orion</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ashterism.com/2025/03/02/trying-orion.html"><![CDATA[<p>Short session last night, only tried a few shoots of M42 - Orion Nebula.  Decided to focus on this nebula for a while and try and use it to learn how to shoot nebulas and understand the processes involved before getting distracted by the idea of upgrading kit etc, so took some initial shoots to learn from.</p>

<p>Exposure time vs trailing going to be an issue.  Tried 3.2sec, 2.5secs, and 1 sec, and various ISOs.  Even 1 sec showed trailing, which isn’t ideal!  Even with trailing though, the images are awe-inspiring - you can actually see the clouds.</p>

<p>On a 2 sec exposure, iso25600 had the best detail, though iso12800 was still good:</p>

<div class="image-grid">
  <figure>
    <img src="/assets/images/25_03/25_03_01_01.png" alt="Photo of Orion Nebula with more of dust clouds showing" />
    <figcaption>2s, iso25600</figcaption>
  </figure>
  <figure>
    <img src="/assets/images/25_03/25_03_01_02.png" alt="Photo of Orion Nebula with less of dust clouds showing" />
    <figcaption>2s, iso12800</figcaption>
  </figure>
</div>

<p>Getting the focus right was also key (see below), but made difficult by even a tiny turn of the focus dials introducing a lot of shake, and then having to track the telescope back to centre once its stopped moving.  Helps me understand why people recommend upgrading the focus mechanism or investing in an autofocus (one day!).</p>

<div class="image-grid">
  <figure>
    <img src="/assets/images/25_03/25_03_01_03.png" alt="Photo of Orion Nebula with some light trailing" />
    <figcaption>3.2 secs at iso8000,  trailing worse and less detail</figcaption>
  </figure>
  <figure>
    <img src="/assets/images/25_03/25_03_01_04.png" alt="Out of focus image of Orion Nebula" />
    <figcaption>Also 3.2secs / iso8000 - but focus wrong here</figcaption>
  </figure>
</div>

<p>-End-</p>]]></content><author><name>Musings by Ash</name></author><category term="astro" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Short session last night, only tried a few shoots of M42 - Orion Nebula. Decided to focus on this nebula for a while and try and use it to learn how to shoot nebulas and understand the processes involved before getting distracted by the idea of upgrading kit etc, so took some initial shoots to learn from.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Early imaging of planets and ursa major</title><link href="https://ashterism.com/2025/03/01/early-imaging.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Early imaging of planets and ursa major" /><published>2025-03-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-03-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ashterism.com/2025/03/01/early-imaging</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ashterism.com/2025/03/01/early-imaging.html"><![CDATA[<p>Last night, I set up a more stable platform using some spare flooring plywood sheets for the telescope in the garden.   It seemed better, but I eventually realised it was still causing wobble so ended up moving the telescope onto the grass.  More successfully, I added a shortcut to my iphone to toggle on/off a red colour filter and turn white point off (make it less bright and red) - just in case I need to look anything up without impacting my night vision too much.</p>

<p>I took some better images of Venus, this time at 1/4000, 1/2000, 1/1000 at iso100.  I think best balance of clarity/brightness at 1/2000 I think, but will have to retry on solid ground.</p>

<div class="image-grid">
  <figure>
    <img src="/assets/images/25_03/25_02_28_01.png" alt="Underexposed not very clear image of Venus" />
    <figcaption>1/4000s, iso100</figcaption>
  </figure>
  <figure>
    <img src="/assets/images/25_03/25_02_28_02.png" alt="Less underexposed slightly clearer image of Venus" />
    <figcaption>1/2000s, iso100</figcaption>
  </figure>
  <figure>
    <img src="/assets/images/25_03/25_02_28_03.png" alt="Bit overexposed not very clear image of Venus" />
    <figcaption>1/1000s, iso100</figcaption>
  </figure>
</div>

<p>Although I was out for sunset, Mercury and Saturn were just too low in the west for me to be able to see due to some trees in that direction.  Keen to look at Saturn when it’s higher in April though.  I tried to find Uranus, but without success.  I did some across the Pleiades though, which caught my attention for much of the evening.</p>

<p>I’m finding myself happily looking through the scope or just my binos more and more, with photography taking a bit of a back seat.  I can definitely see myself doing more of both - certainly in the warmer months when I’ve worked out how to sit and observe rather than stand (or contort myself around) the scope for long periods in the cold.</p>

<p>Pleiades shots weren’t great, and didn’t match up to what I could see in the scope.  I will try this again with the telescope on firmer ground though. I did particularly like this string of stars you can see in the image below, nestled into the Pleiades cluster</p>

<figure>
  <img src="/assets/images/25_03/25_02_28_04.png" alt="String of stars in Pleiades cluster" />
  <figcaption>0.5 sec at iso6400 (any slower exposure had trails due to wobble)</figcaption>
</figure>

<p>It was Jupiter that made me realise I had a serious wobble issue when I couldn’t get a clearer image than below left.  After moving the telescope onto the grass I got a better image, with the bands just starting to be visible.  This isn’t far off what I could see in the scope, though I suspect I can capture a lot better detail I learn and practice more.</p>

<div class="image-grid">
  <figure>
    <img src="/assets/images/25_03/25_02_28_05.png" alt="Blurred light trail" />
    <figcaption>Blurred image of Jupiter</figcaption>
  </figure>
  <figure>
    <img src="/assets/images/25_03/25_02_28_06.png" alt="Image of Jupiter" />
    <figcaption>Clearer image of Jupiter, though still low on detail</figcaption>
  </figure>
</div>

<p>Otherwise, I took some shots of Ursa Major and Minor together, then mostly played around with some light painting ideas - though one for another time.</p>

<figure>
    <img src="/assets/images/25_03/25_02_28_07.png" alt="Starscape showing the Big Dipper (Ursa Major), silhouette of tree on rightside of image" />
    <figcaption>15s, iso3200</figcaption>
  </figure>

<figure>
    <img src="/assets/images/25_03/25_02_28_08.png" alt="Image of Big Dipper with less background stars" />
    <figcaption>15s, iso200 - less light, less detail
</figcaption>
  </figure>]]></content><author><name>Musings by Ash</name></author><category term="astro" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Last night, I set up a more stable platform using some spare flooring plywood sheets for the telescope in the garden. It seemed better, but I eventually realised it was still causing wobble so ended up moving the telescope onto the grass. More successfully, I added a shortcut to my iphone to toggle on/off a red colour filter and turn white point off (make it less bright and red) - just in case I need to look anything up without impacting my night vision too much.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Simple stargazing</title><link href="https://ashterism.com/2025/03/01/stargazing-with-binos.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Simple stargazing" /><published>2025-03-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-03-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ashterism.com/2025/03/01/stargazing-with-binos</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ashterism.com/2025/03/01/stargazing-with-binos.html"><![CDATA[<p>Last night I sat in my dad’s garden with him and looked up at the sky.</p>

<p>We had a couple of deckchairs and some blankets, and though I had the telescope set up,  we mostly used our unaided eyes and binoculars to look up and enjoy the starscape.</p>

<p>It’s a really enjoyable way to spend an evening, chatting and taking in the amazing night skies (bortle 4).  I talked through want I’d been learning about the night skies, and how they will move about the garden as the seasons change.  Talking with my dad helped me realise I’d learnt quite a lot from what the stars actually are (how far away, what they are made of etc), and useful things like how to use the big dipper / orion to find other stars.</p>

<p>I didn’t keep a log, but from memory we looked at:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Orion (and it’s stars)</li>
  <li>Orion nebula (through the telescope)</li>
  <li>Big dipper / Ursa Major</li>
  <li>Polaris</li>
  <li>Little Dipper /Ursa Minor(harder to find)</li>
  <li>Jupiter</li>
  <li>Mars</li>
  <li>Pleiades</li>
  <li>Caster</li>
  <li>Pollux
…and looked up and looked at some of the constellations</li>
</ul>

<p>It really is amazing how much more you can see with binoculars.  I was skeptical of all the comments on “how to get into astronomy” posts that you should start with a good pair of binoculars, but you absolutely should!</p>

<p>Nice to just sit, chat, and look at the stars..</p>]]></content><author><name>Musings by Ash</name></author><category term="astro" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Last night I sat in my dad’s garden with him and looked up at the sky.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Getting acquainted</title><link href="https://ashterism.com/2025/02/28/gettingAcquainted.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Getting acquainted" /><published>2025-02-28T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ashterism.com/2025/02/28/gettingAcquainted</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ashterism.com/2025/02/28/gettingAcquainted.html"><![CDATA[<p>In anticipation of the much talked about planetary alignment on the 28th (tonight!) I got out a few times this week to familiarise myself with the stars and the telescope.  I’ve started reading “Nightwatch”, which is excellently written for the newbie, and really feeding my sense of awe and wonder at the universe - and giving some helpful pointers to actually get started.</p>

<p>Key amongst these, is that you can start to learn to navigate the stars by just learning the Big Dipper and Orion - as these point to various other stars and constellations.</p>

<p>My mind is a bit blown by Orion nebula.  Just sat there in the middle of Orion literally generating stars…</p>

<p>Anyway, I took a few photos of Venus - with my Camera (Canon R7 with 100-400mm) and also through the Skywatcher 200p.  On review, I needed a much shorter shutter speed - I used 1/30th and above, but will try 1/250 and 1/1000 next time, sticking with a low iso.</p>

<figure>
  <img src="/assets/images/25_03/25_02_27_01.png" alt="Very over exposured image of Venus" />
  <figcaption>0.5 sec - way too over exposed.</figcaption>
</figure>

<figure>
  <img src="/assets/images/25_03/25_02_27_02.png" alt="Over exposured image of Venus" />
  <figcaption>1/30th - still over exposed.</figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Also took some pictures of Mars, Orion, and the Big Dipper / Ursa Major with the R7/ 16mm.  They came out better, but still some blurring as using longer exposures (15-30 secs).  Without a tracker you get the trails, so I will try 5,10,15 secs and some higher ISOs next time.</p>

<figure>
  <img src="/assets/images/25_03/25_02_27_3.png" alt="Picture of Orion constellation in night sky" />
  <figcaption>Orion - 1*30sec.</figcaption>
</figure>

<figure>
  <img src="/assets/images/25_03/25_02_27_4.png" alt="Faint photo of Big Dipper (asterism)" />
  <figcaption>Big Dipper - 1*30sec  - not as bad, but still gives an “out of focus” appearance.</figcaption>
</figure>

<p>However, getting better at actually getting the focus right (just back from actual infinite it seems), and did get a nice (slightly tweaked in lightroom) pic of the Big Dipper with trees in the foreground (perhaps more by accident than design!).  I think I need to worry less about the pictures looking too dark ‘in the field’ and lean into post-processing to balance lighting etc.  Even when images look great on my high-res laptop screen, they need brightening for posting online or sharing with friends etc anyway.</p>

<figure>
  <img src="/assets/images/25_03/25_02_27_5.png" alt="Big Dipper asterism above silhouetted trees" />
  <figcaption>Canon 16mm, f/2.8, 30s, iso125.</figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Next time I’m out going to try some of the planets again, and also the same Orion/Big Dipper asterims to try and lock in the settings, and help me with remembering their utility as signposts.</p>]]></content><author><name>Musings by Ash</name></author><category term="astro" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In anticipation of the much talked about planetary alignment on the 28th (tonight!) I got out a few times this week to familiarise myself with the stars and the telescope. I’ve started reading “Nightwatch”, which is excellently written for the newbie, and really feeding my sense of awe and wonder at the universe - and giving some helpful pointers to actually get started.]]></summary></entry></feed>